Finding Aid for Klaus F. Riegel Papers 1955-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Klaus F. Riegel Papers 1955-1977
Riegel, Klaus F.
Professor of psychology and member of the Institute of Gerontology of the University of Michigan. Correspondence, conference and symposium files, teaching materials, grant proposals and reports, and papers and reprints; also papers of Ruth Riegel.
861063 Aa 2
15 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Riegel papers were given to the Institute of Gerontology in 1978. They were subsequently transferred to the library in 1984 (donor no. 6160 ).
The collection is open for research.
Klaus Riegel, 1925-1977, was born in Berlin, Germany and worked as a metal worker in a shipyard before his admission to the University of Hamburg. Initially Riegel studied physics and mathematics but later turned to psychology. Riegel first came to the United States to pursue an M.A. degree at the University of Minnesota, which he completed in 1955. His Ph.D. was granted by the University of Hamburg in 1958, after which he spent a postdoctoral year as a Visiting Scientist at the National Institute of Health. In 1959, Riegel joined the faculty of the University of Michigan Department of Psychology. In addition to his teaching responsibilities, Riegel participated in the Psycholinguistics program, the Institute of Gerontology, and the Center for Human Growth and Development. Outside activities included election as a fellow to the Gerontology Society and the American Psychological Association, service on the executive committee of the International Society for the Study of Behavioral Development, and as President of the Psychological and Social Sciences Section of the Gerontological Society. From 1970-1977 Riegel served as editor of Human Development. In 1976, the Gerontological Society awarded Klaus Riegel the Robert W. Kleemier Award for contributions to the field. Throughout his career, Riegel was an active writer and lecturer, contributing to journals and participating in conferences related to his interests in language and cognitive development and functions, the aging process, history of the social sciences, and the developing discipline of dialectical psychology. Precise dates of appointments and an extensive bibliography of his published work are included in the collection.
The Klaus Riegel papers, 1955-1977, document his educational, professional, and research activities in the discipline of psychology. The collection includes correspondence, grant applications, and progress reports, research reports, unpublished papers, reprints, lecture notes and transcriptions, syllabi and handouts, examinations, and conference programs. Riegel's specific interests within the discipline of psychology included developmental psychology of the aged, psycholinguistics, and history of the social sciences. Riegel's research activity in these areas was conducted under grant funding. Scope, objectives, and results of various research projects will be found in the Grant Materials series. While a few of the grant applications were to support graduate-level education, the Teaching Materials series contains course-related materials used by Riegel in his classes, most of which were offered through the Psychology department. Professional activity was a large part of Riegel's career. The Correspondence and Conferences and Symposia series are strongly related and illustrate the active role Riegel played in professional and theoretical development.
Subjects:
Gerontology.; Riegel, Klaus F.; Riegel, Ruth.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute of Gerontology.
- Biographical material
  The Biographical Material file (1 in.) includes a vitae, an obituary published in Human Development, and bibliographies of Riegel's published work. One of these bibliographies, arranged in chronological order, serves as a partial index to the Papers and Reprints series.
  - Vitae, bibliography, obituary (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1959-1976
  Two folders of general correspondence 1959-1976 (6 in.), arranged alphabetically by correspondent relate to his professional and research pursuits. The remaining folders are arranged alphabetically by association and provide further information on conference topics and organization and association issues.
  - General 1959-1968
    - A-I (Box 1)
    - J-Z (Box 1)
  - American Psychological Association. Division 26 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Dialectical Psychology, Newsletter 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Gerontological Society 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - International Association of Gerontology 1966-1972 (Box 1)
  - International Society for the Study of Behavioral Development
    - 1970-1975 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee 1973-1976 (Box 1)
- Conferences and Symposia 1957-1972
  Arranged alphabetically, the Conferences and Symposia files, 1957-1977 (6 in.) include programs, background papers or abstracts, rosters of participants, and correspondence. Riegel's research interests in developmental psychology of the aging, the history and philosophy of psychology, and the emerging discipline of dialectical psychology are strongly in evidence here. Some folders contain materials in German, particularly the following: Biometrisches Killoquium 1957, German Psychological Association 1974, and the Konstanz Conference, 1973.
  - Presentations
    - 1959-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1976 (Box 1)
  - Biometrisches Kolloquium 1957 (Box 1)
  - Dialectical Psychology 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - German Psychological Association 1974 (Box 1)
  - International Society for the Study of Behavioral Development
    - Biennial Meeting 1973 (Box 1)
    - Satellite Symposium, Israel 1975 (Box 1)
  - Issues in Developmental and Historical Structuralism 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Konstanz Conference-"Probleme des Strukturgegriffs in den Sozialwissenschaften," 1973 (Box 1)
  - SRCD Symposia
    - "Strategies for the Analysis and Explication of Age Changes," 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Cognitive Developmental Psychology-What Next?" 1973 (Box 1)
  - Science, Technology, and Future Societies Seminar 1975 (Box 1)
  - Study of Dialectical Operations 1974 (Box 1)
- Teaching Materials 1958-1977
  Arranged by department and course number, the Teaching Materials series, 1958-1977 (1 lin. ft.) relates primarily to psychology department classes taught by Riegel. The series includes syllabi, reading lists, outlines, exams, lecture notes and transcriptions (particularly for Psych. 451) memoranda and correspondence, and student evaluations. Also included is an evaluation for the Psycholinguistics program and correspondence related to the administration of that program.
  - Developmental Psychology (Box 2)
  - Human Development
    - HD308 "Personality and Aging" (Box 2)
  - Psychology Department
    - Memoranda and Correspondence 1960-1974 (Box 2)
    - History of Department (Box 2)
    - Preliminary Exam Questions (Box 2)
    - Course Materials
      - History Seminars 1968-1974 (Box 2)
      - Psych. 100, 108, 117, 301, 413 1961-1975 (Box 2)
      - Psych. 192, "Perception and Cognition" (Box 2)
      - Psych. 302-303, "Seminar on Verbal Behavior" (Box 2)
      - Psych. 443, "Psychology of Language"
        - Handouts 1962-1965 (Box 2)
        - Lecture Notes (Box 2)
      - Psych. 451, "Development of Language and Cognitive Functions"
        - Handouts and Exams 1970-1977 (Box 2)
        - Lecture Transcriptions
          - January-February, 1974 (Box 2)
          - March-April, 1974 (Box 2)
      - Psych. 489, "History of Psychology," 1967-1974 (Box 2)
      - Psych. 578, "History of Psychology" (Box 2)
      - Psych. 751, "Developmental Psychology," 1958-1960 (Box 2)
      - Psych. 758, "Psychology of Aging" (Box 2)
      - Psych. 846, "Seminar on Language" (Box 2)
      - Psych. 948, "Black Psychology" (Box 2)
    - Psycholinguistics
      - Program Evaluation 1973-1976 (Box 2)
      - Seminar 1967 (Box 2)
      - Students and Staff (Box 2)
- Grant Material 1955-1976
  Divided into Proposals and Research Reports, the Grant Material series, 1955-1976. (1.5 lin. ft.) indicates the research activity and trends pursued by Riegel and his associates in the Psychology Department. Proposals indicate the scope, objectives, and methodology of a project and often include initial and renewal applications, budget statements, related correspondence, and progress reports on grant administration. The Research Reports are the final products from three of these proposals for which Riegel served as project director. One of these projects, "The Aging of Older Persons," was conducted at the University of Hamburg. The other two projects were carried out at the University of Michigan. For the "Development of Language Functions" project, there is a list of technical reports which serves as an index.
  - Evaluations and site visits by Riegel 1970-1976 (Box 3)
  - Proposals
    - "The acquisition of verbal processes and their utilization in intellectual and motor performance," 1968 (Box 3)
    - "Adulthood and Aging," Training Grant (Box 3)
    - Aging 1955-1965 (Box 3)
    - "Analysis of Word Meaning"
      - Applications 1962-1963 (Box 3)
      - Budget 1963-1967 (Box 3)
    - "Development of Language Functions"
      - Applications 1964-1967 (Box 3)
      - Progress Reports 1965-1968, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Developmental Psycholinguistics, Training Grant 1968-1974 (Box 3)
    - Developmental Psychology, Training Grant
      - 1964 (Box 3)
      - circa 1976 (Box 3)
    - "Dialogic Research in Education," 1976 (Box 3)
    - Psycholinguistics, Training Grant 1968-1974 (Box 3)
    - "Psychological Studies of Bilingual Performances and Cross Linguistic Differences," 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - "Socio-Psychological Studies in the History of Science," 1971 (Box 3)
    - "Studies in Social Conflict, History of Science, and 'Radical Thinking'," 1970 (Box 3)
    - "Study on the Use of Association and Fluency Tests," 1960-1962 (Box 3)
  - Research Reports
    - Aging of Older Persons, Technical Reports 1-3 1957-1958 (Box 3)
    - Analysis of Word Meaning Project
      - Reports 1-3 (Box 3)
      - Reports 4-8 (Box 3)
      - Reports 9-13 (Box 3)
    - Development of Language Functions Project
      - List of technical reports 1968 (Box 4)
      - Reports 1, 3-8 (Box 4)
      - Reports 12, 14-17 (Box 4)
      - Reports 18-20 (Box 4)
      - Reports 22-24 (Box 4)
      - Reports 28-31 (Box 4)
      - Reports 35-37, 39 (Box 4)
      - Reports 42-45 (Box 4)
      - Reports 46-49 (Box 4)
      - Reports 53-54, 57-58, 60, 62 (Box 4)
      - Reports 67, 71-72, 74 (Box 4)
- Papers and Reprints 1955-1977
  Arranged chronologically, or alphabetically by title if no date could be determined, Papers and Reprints, 1955-1977 (1.25 lin ft.) can be accessed more easily by using the chronological bibliography to be found in the folder of Biographical Materials. Some reprints are in German, particularly in the years 1955-1959 and 1962. Some book reviews and unpublished presentations, as well as a paper on the history of Philosophy submitted for admission to the University of Hamburg are included in this series which is largely composed of reprints.
  - Philosophy, History of (Box 4)
  - Undated
    - A-M (Box 4)
    - N-P (Box 4)
    - Q-S (Box 4)
    - T-Z (Box 5)
  - 1955-1958 (Box 5)
  - 1959-1963 (Box 5)
  - 1964-1969 (Box 5)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - 1972-1975 (Box 5)
  - 1976 (Box 5)
  - Psychology of Development and History, 1976 (Box 5)
  - 1977 (Box 5)
- Ruth Riegel, 1956-1960
  An active researcher and educator, the papers of Ruth Riegel, 1956-1960 (2 in.) includes only those articles and papers which appeared in her name only. Produced before moving to the United States, these papers are all in German. Articles which she co-authored with husband Klaus, which were many, have been interfiled with his reprints.
  - Biographical Material (Box 5)
  - Papers and Reprints (Box 5)
- Writings of Others
  The Writings of Others (10 lin. ft.) series consists of two sub-series: materials arranged alphabetically by author, and materials arranged alphabetically by subject. Published reprints have been eliminated from this file.
  - Arranged alphabetically (Box 6)
  - Arranged alphabetically (Box 7)
    (continued)
  - Arranged alphabetically (Box 8)
  - Arranged alphabetically (Box 9)
  - Arranged alphabetically (Box 10)
  - Arranged alphabetically (Box 11)
  - Arranged alphabetically (Box 12)
  - Arranged alphabetically (Box 13)
  - Arranged by subject (Box 13)
  - Arranged by subject (Box 14)
  - Arranged by subject (Box 15)